<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the life of Christina Queen of Svveden: with her resignation of the crown, voyage to Bruxels, and journey to Rome. Whereunto is added, her Genius. / Translated out of French, by I.H.</title>
            <title>Briève relation de la vie de Christine reyne de Suède. English</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3803</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E870_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200881</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861507</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861507</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113644</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79464)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113644)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 131:E870[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the life of Christina Queen of Svveden: with her resignation of the crown, voyage to Bruxels, and journey to Rome. Whereunto is added, her Genius. / Translated out of French, by I.H.</title>
                  <title>Briève relation de la vie de Christine reyne de Suède. English</title>
                  <author>Chevreau, Urbain, 1613-1701,</author>
                  <author>Saint-Maurice, Mr,</author>
                  <author>Leti, Gregorio, 1630-1701,</author>
                  <author>Howell, John, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for Henry Fletcher, at the Gilt Cups; and Nath. Heathcoate, at the Acorne, neer the West-end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, sometimes attributed to John Howell, of "Briève relation de la vie de Christine reyne de Suède, iusqu'à la demission de sa couronne &amp; son arrivement à Bruxelles", and "Le génie de la reyne Christine de Suède".</note>
                  <note>"Briève relation de la vie de Christine" is apparently erroneously attributed to Urbain Chevreau, secretary to Kristina in the early 1650's, by Halkett &amp; Laing and Wing; NUC attributes the work to Gregorio Leti on the grounds that "A version with title: L'adieu des franc̜ois à la Suède, is in his Le portrait et la vie secrette de la reine Christine de Suède.".</note>
                  <note>"Le génie de la reyne Christine de Suède" is wrongly attributed to Urbain Chevreau, and was apparently composed by a Mr. Saint-Maurice, as a vengeful satire against Kristina (cf. Barbier).</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 26".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kristina, --  Queen of Sweden, 1626-1689 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113644:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RELATION, Of the LIFE OF <hi>CHRISTINA</hi> Queen of Svveden: WITH Her
<list>
                  <item>Reſignation of the Crown,</item>
                  <item>Voyage to <hi>Bruxels,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>Journey to <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto is added, Her Genius.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of French, by <hi>I. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>Henry Fletcher,</hi> at the three Gilt Cups; and <hi>Nath. Heathcoate,</hi> at the Acorne, neer the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113644:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113644:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Trange have been the Revolutions produced in our Age; and ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, as may beget admiration in the moſt Grave and Wiſe. But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others, this of <hi>Chriſtina</hi> of <hi>Sweden</hi> is tranſcendent. That great Queen had worthily obtained the repute of being not ſo great and glorious, as wiſe and vertuous: the rays of her glory were ſo reſplendent upon her People, at her firſt appearing, that the loſs of her renowned father <hi>Guſtavus,</hi> that bright Star, was little perceived, by reaſon of the ſweet influences caſt from the more refulgent brightneſs of this riſing Sun. But a Sunſhine-morning proves not always a fair day: nor did this Luminary long continue her luſtre, but became ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured and darkned by certain foggie vapours exhaled by herſelf. To ſpeak plainly, <hi>Pigmentelli</hi> and others fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting that Court, inſinuated themſelves into the Queens favour and familiarity, whereby they got oportunity to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtil into her ſuch counſels as were the natural products of
<pb facs="tcp:113644:3"/>
their own baſe hearts; which ſhe embracing became quite changed; and her Court, which was formerly a School of Vertue, was now a Nurſery of Vice, which having once found an inlet, ruſhed in like an overflowing Inundation, drowning the plants, and even waſhing away the ſeeds of Vertue, that had been ſowed and ſprung therein. In a word, Vice, that had been rarely ſeen in that Court, became now a conſtant gueſt, and found entertainment both at bed and board.</p>
            <p>The enſuing Diſcourſe gives you an ample account of this Princeſs, both while in her glory, and after her eclipſe; being written by one of her Domeſticks, who was privie to her moſt ſecret practices, both in <hi>Sweden,</hi> and alſo thorow <hi>Germany</hi> to <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> where ſhe gave him and the reſt that accompanied her (except ſome few) the go-by, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them to ſhift for themſelves in a ſtrange Country, (for ſo it was to moſt of them) without any conſideration or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion on her part.</p>
            <p>Never was the World ſo gull'd in their opinions of any one perſon, as of this Princeſs, who whilſt ſhe was eſteemed the Phoenix of the Age, became inſenſibly a prodigious mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; and from a Lady of great renown, ſhe is become a Lady Errant, ſeeking Adventures in ſtrange Lands.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113644:3"/>
            <head>A brief RELATION of the Life of <hi>CHRISTINA</hi> Queen of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll Europe (not to ſpeak of the other parts of the earth) has doubtleſs heard of the Reſignation of CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STINA Queen of Sweden. The Ignorant, who are but little vers'd in Policie, have look'd on it, as a Prodigie of Vertue, and an action full of Generoſity: but the Learned and Politick have taken it, as the higheſt Folly, which could ere fall into a womans head; and who is beſt inform'd of the affairs and ſtate of the Kingdom of Swedland, doth publiſh it with a loud voice, for a famous Bankrupt, ſhe would make to her Creditors. The leſs judicious have believ'd, that the Swedes being weary of her Government, for the moſt part diſorderly, ſhe hath been (as it were) ſecretly forc'd, to deveſt her ſelf willingly of the Kingdom, to prevent with prudence what might befal ſome other way. But the wiſeſt, who know the light and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant humour of that Princeſs, ſay boldly, that ſhe hath
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113644:4"/>
done it through levity, and out of a whimſey; having always been carryed thus, in whatſoever ſhe hath done. I omit purpoſely many ſpeeches, I have heard upon this ſubject, in Denmark, Germany, the Low-Countries, and even in Swedland; becauſe I ſee no motives ſtrong enough, to make me believe them.</p>
            <p>That Princeſs was cry'd up, the firſt years of her Reign, amongſt all Nations in Europe; and truely with reaſon: for in thoſe days ſhe might juſtly be call'd, The moſt Religious, Juſt, and Vertuous Princeſs in the world. She was familiar and beneficial to all, very charitable to the needy, and moſt officious to any, to whom ſhe might either do, or procure any good. But a monſter, France had brought forth 'gainſt her cuſtom, being gone to lurk in the Caves, Foreſts and Rocks, which the Goths left of old, to breathe the air of France and Italy, did ſo skilfully win her heart, yea poſſeſs'd it, that all the time he ſtay'd there, he handled her at his pleaſure, and for his own profit; but to the grief and diſcontent of all the world, yea of the chief of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, who weary with the impertinencies of a man of nothing, did twice or thrice attempt upon his life. That man being without Religion and Piety, impreſs'd all his falſe opinions on the minde of the Queen, whom thus in a ſhort time he did make like himſelf; and ſhe was in a moment ſo ſtrangely chang'd, that ſhe was no more like herſelf. She did indeed bear ſtill the name of Great CHRISTINA, but ſhe had no more her vertues. She did before, eat for the moſt part in publike, where they us'd to diſcourſe of ſome fine matters, wherein all her Court did with admiration partake of the knowledge and ſubtilty of that Princeſs's wit; who by thoſe means was reverenc'd and cheriſh'd by all men. But this fooliſh States-man, quite contrary to that commendable
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113644:4"/>
practice, ſtole her from her Courtiers, to poſſeſs her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and entertain her Royal minde, with Jeſts and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous Sports; ſo that her Counſellors, and the great men of the Kingdom, could hardly ſee her, and ſeldom ſpeak to her. By her privacie with that baſe fellow, ſhe began to loſe much of the good opinion, her Subjects had of her; and her aſſiduity with him did ſo eloign the moſt zealous of her Courtiers, that her Court did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear like a Deſert or Solitude, to what it was before.</p>
            <p>The imprudence or impudence of that mercenary ſtranger, did not onely affront the chief of the Kingdom, and even thoſe who were moſt in the Queens favour, but did alſo moleſt her domeſticks; injuring them one after another, rather by Fancie then Reaſon. And this he did, to make oſtentation of the power, he had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd upon the minde of CHRISTINA, which he cauſed to act according to the ſtrange motion of his ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular paſſions; and into which he might eaſily inſpire love or hatred, with their effects, in the behalf, or to the prejudice of whom he pleas'd.</p>
            <p>That Imprudence and Impudence grew at laſt to that height, that being judg'd intolerable, ſome did reſolve and endeavour to murther him. This will appear ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what violent and bloody, to calm or ſtill humours: but it is fit, one man ſhould die for all: and when all ſuch wicked and abominable perſons ſhould be cut off, the reſt would fare better, and live with more content. This baſe and fearful heart, which hath never done any thing which either were generous, or appear'd as ſuch, ſeeing himſelf purſu'd in good earneſt, was forc'd to think on his retreat, for which he made an advantageous provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; carrying out of the Kingdom, whether in Coyn or Plate, to the value of an hundred thouſand Crowns, and more. And it is a ſtrange thing, that ſtout Nation
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113644:5"/>
had not a man, who would purſue this infamous Fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, to waſh in his foul blood ſo many crimes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he had defil'd that Court. Providence would not have it ſo. His abſence did indeed give ſome reſpite to many men, and did ſweeten their bitterneſs: but he had ſpread too violent a Poyſon in the Queens minde, and had left there too ſtrong impreſſions of evil, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that the Court ſhould recover its former ſtate; it being the nature of that Princeſs, never to be conſtant, but in thoſe things, which have blaſted her fame. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs many of thoſe, who ſaw thoſe diſorders, will eaſily imagine, of whom I ſpeak: But to ſatisfie all the world, and that no man perſwade himſelf, I have invented this, I do ingenuouſly confeſs, that the Picture I have now drawn of a Monſter, of a mercenary and impudent fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, of a man of nothing, of a baſe heart, and, in a word, of an Atheiſt, is that of <hi>Bourdelot,</hi> who, like a great Maſtiff, eats this day the bread of the poor, and ſucks the blood of the Crucifix; having obtain'd an Abbey of the King of France, by the urgent interceſſion of CHRISTINA, who took ſo much to heart the get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of that Benefice, (which Rome, inform'd of <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delot</hi>'s ill qualities, had refus'd him) that ſhe ceas'd not her importunities to the Court of France, till ſhe ſaw her Dagon ſit in the Temple of God. This Monſter then being ſhamefully expell'd out of Swedland, the Queen hath ſince conſtantly ſhew'd her ſelf ſuch, as he did leave her, that is, a Lady without Religion, Piety, Vertue, and Fidelity; diſſolute in her life, and libertine in her ſpeeches; a cheat, ſlanderer, and jeerer; and of whom one might truly ſay, She had nothing Royal, but the Kingdom. Who will not wonder at ſo ſtrange and prodigious a change? Who will not ſay, That Queen is fallen from an eminent ſtate to a lowe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113644:5"/>
But you, brave Sweds, will you not weep, to ſee the flow'r of your Kingdom ſo much wither'd, your Amarantha ſo much chang'd; and your Princeſs, who has been long the wonder of this Age, the glory of her Sex, and the ſubject of the whole worlds admiration, be now the May-game of all Nations? To ſee your Queen, who heretofore was cheriſh'd and eſteem'd by all in general, now become their by-word and laughing-ſtock? Yes, all your eyes ſhould now be turn'd into as many ſprings of tears, to weep perpetually ſuch a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal downfal, if divine providence, which would not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake your Kingdom, had not rais'd you a religious, wiſe, vertuous, valiant, and all-generous King, who may worthily govern you all his life, as you may in reaſon expect from his fair beginnings. And you, ingenious French, will you not ſigh and groan, that your Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrix has her hands ſhut to do you good, and can no more beſtow her Bounties upon you: that ſhe who has ſo dearly cheriſh'd your Nation, for your Poets, Muſicians and Dancers, and chiefly for your Gallantry, is now ſeeking her beſt delights amongſt your moſt cruel ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: and finally, that ſhe, who did formerly protect you, hath now forſaken you? Yet I perſwade my ſelf, that being of late accuſtom'd to be ill us'd by that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, you will ſoon dry your tears, and it will better be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come you to leave the Gothiſh Land for yours: you are not welcom there, but much envied; quit it then with, or after me: I left there many of my friends and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance in that reſolution.</p>
            <p>But let's return to our Princeſs, who in truth was for a long time, as I have ſaid, very pious and religious: but ſince, ſhe hath been ſeen doubting, whether there be a God and a Providence, and denying Heaven and Hell, Saints and Devils, Judgement and Reſurrection, and ſo
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113644:6"/>
conſequently the Souls Immortalitie. Concerning Chriſts Incarnation, 'tis but a Fiction in her opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Who has not frequented her Court, will hardly believe this: but who has been there during her Reign, will not give me the lye. She hath often made Speeches in full Aſſemblies, which ſufficiently ſhew'd her ſence. I am witneſs of it, and can paſs for an irrefragable one before thoſe who know me. A man of probity, and whoſe profeſſion permits him not to lye, chiefly in ſuch an occaſion, hath told me in private, that he had divers times entertain'd the Queen three or four hours, about the exiſtence of a Deitie, and concerning a Providence, which governs all things in the world; wherein he had found her very wavering, and making uſe of all the ſtrongeſt Arguments which Libertines have forg'd, to oppoſe thoſe Truths. Yet there is ſome probabilitie, that what that Princeſs did in thoſe ſtrange Diſputes, was rather to ſhew her fine wit, then out of a deſigne to overthrow thoſe Truths ſo well eſtabliſh'd in the world, that none but Fools will oppoſe them; ſince na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural lights are ſufficient in thoſe, who have the right uſe of Reaſon, to give them the knowledge thereof. Hers are too bright and great, to permit her to doubt of thoſe high Myſteries: and I am charitably perſwaded, that 'twas rather to exerciſe her wit and rare know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as School-men put theirs forth, in the very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their Theologie, diſputing whether there be a God, who is the object of that noble Science; then by any belief or opinion, which be criminal before God, or injurious unto his exiſtence. Yet it muſt be confeſs'd, that our Princeſs hath been obſetv'd, to call ſo often thoſe high things in queſtion, ſo ready to ſpeak againſt them, and ſo looſe in all ſuch diſcourſes, that thence many did ſuſpect her to be ill grounded in her Religion:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113644:6"/>
and ſhe was often heard ſay after a Sermon, that ſhe did know leſs then before: and where her Prieſts or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters took exception at her, yea preach'd againſt her, chiefly becauſe there was a room full of naked Pictures appointed to pray, praiſe, reade, preach, (they were Pictures repreſenting the Creation of our firſt parents, a little too much to the life) ſhe did reply, that they ſhew'd well their ignorance thereby, not to know that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> were both created ſtark naked; and that it was lawful, to make their pictures in the ſame faſhion, as they came out of the hands of God; and that the Idea's of a Painter were not more criminal then his. 'Tis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry true, ſhe hath loſt much of her good name, in th' opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of all pious and modeſt ſouls, ſince <hi>Bourdelot</hi>'s in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal acquaintance with her, by her licentious liberty, in making her moſt delightful and familiar conferences of laſcivious ſpeeches, tales or ſtories full of obſcenity, in whoſe relation ſhe takes moſt pleaſure, and will ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely that ev'ry thing be call'd by its own name, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any diſguiſe, or that ſeaſoning and grain of ſalt, which modeſtie inſpires to all its profeſſors, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons well educated.</p>
            <p>One of my friends, who upon his admiſſion into her Service, was us'd to entertain her both often and long, obſerving that her minde was delighted with ſuch kinde of tales, did abundantly furniſh her with them: yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there were ſome of his narrations, which did ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times require more modeſt expreſſions, then the genuine or natural, chiefly before a Royal Majeſtie, and in a maids preſence; as ſhe ſaw him going about his cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumlocutions, and ſeeking civil terms, ſhe would boldly ſpeak out the words, though they were never ſo filthy; many of which he hath ſpecified to me, which modeſtie forbids me to write here. Judge of her Religion, by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113644:7"/>
her ranging up and down the world without a Miniſter; preferring her health, (for whoſe preſervation ſhe hath a Phyſician) to her ſouls ſalvation, for which thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are inſtruments, appointed by God. She made a ſhew to retain one, who did wait on her as far as Halmſtat, upon the frontiers of Denmark, where ſhe did diſmiſs him. Another was offered her at Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, whom ſhe made a ſhew to accept, though the event declar'd, ſhe had no minde to him. And indeed, ſuch perſons had been but as thorns in her feet: for, having a deſigne to profeſs Popery, the Miniſters of the Goſpel were no fit attendants on her. 'Tis evident, that long before, ſhe took no delight in all their Functions: for, as many perſons can teſtifie, as well as I, ſhe had at Church ſo little Religion and Zeal, that her countenance ſhew'd enough, what ſpirit poſſeſs'd her. She us'd to ſit in a Chair of Purple Velvet, and lean her head and arms on another; queſtionleſs building (after the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb) fine Caſtles in the air: and if the Miniſter, through his zeal to his Charge, or for the merit of his Theme or Subject, did preach and pray a little too long, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion of the Queen and all ſuch luke-warm ſouls, her cuſtom was, to recreate her weary attention, (if yet ſhe had any at all) in playing with two little Spaniels, which are always with her; or pratling with ſome of her crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, if any was then neer. I have ſometimes ſeen her make ſuch a noiſe with her Fan on her Chair, that if the Prieſt had had reſpect and complaiſance enough, to give ſomthing to her humour, he had taken thoſe ſignes of impatience, as ſilent commands to make a quick end: but he was no whit the ſhorter; either becauſe he kept his old cuſtom, or that he would break or bend her im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient diſpoſition, and uſe her to more pietie, attention, modeſtie, in the celebration of Divine Myſteries, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113644:7"/>
ſo in the ſweet exerciſe of Chriſtian Religion: which yet could take no effect on her Mind, ſo ſtrong and laſting are <hi>Bourdelot</hi>'s impreſſions on her, and ſo deep all the roots, which the ſeed of Impiety and Diſſolution, he ſow'd in her heart, hath taken there, that no amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can be expected from her.</p>
            <p>That inconſtant Humor has continu'd with her, even in ſtrange Countries, &amp; namely at <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> where we ſaw her at Church, hearing the Word of God, with ſo little reverence &amp; attention, &amp; ſo much impatience, that thereby many men, who went to ſee her through curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, were confirm'd in the ill Opinion, they had before conceiv'd of her, by divers Reports made of her, before her Arrival. Even ſome of her Swediſh Prieſts, having Obſerv'd ſo little Zeal in their Princeſs, told me before my departure, out of that cold Country, That they fear'd very much, ſhe would fondly embrace the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions of Papiſts, ſince ſhe ſlighted ſo viſibly the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſhe was bred in, and lov'd not the other, which is known by the name of the Reformed Churches, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving frequently ſaid, <hi>She had rather become a Papiſt, than of the Reform'd Religion;</hi> meaning by this, thoſe of <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va</hi>'s Confeſſion, from whom ſhe had a mighty Averſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; either becauſe ſhe was not well inform'd of her Doctrine and Purity, or that the <hi>Lutheran,</hi> in which ſhe has been bred, comes ſomwhat neerer the Roman, chiefly in Ceremonies.</p>
            <p>But it is enough of her Religion, (which is now loſt, if ever ſhe had ſincerely any) let's a little Examine her Carriage, in her Wandrings, or Voyages. It was thought convenient, That after ſhe had waited on the Queen her Mother, whoſe ordinary abode is at <hi>Niuku<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin,</hi> ſhe ſhould go to <hi>Oeland,</hi> which is a very pleaſant Iſle, that ſhe had reſerv'd for her ſelf, and did before
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113644:8"/>
belong to his Royal Highneſs, who doth now Reign o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Sweds, a Nation (though glorious) yet too little for his Merits and aſpiring Valour. Thence ſhe was to paſs by Sea into <hi>Pomerania,</hi> to ſee the Lands and Goods, which were Aſſign'd for her Appannage or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, by her own Agreement: The King gave Order that Seven Great Ships ſhould be prepar'd for her Tranſportation, under the Command of Marſhal <hi>Wrangle;</hi> and that the Governor of <hi>Oeland</hi> ſhould have in readineſs whatſoever was fit to entertain her Royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as it became his and her Majeſty: But having made a ſhew to go thither, yea, being gone that way a whole day, ſhe did reſolve to go by Land, and to croſs all <hi>Denmark,</hi> which ſhe did, habited like a Cavalier, with a red Scarf after the Spaniſh <hi>mode,</hi> and thus entred <hi>Hamburgh incognito,</hi> and went to Lodge in the Houſe of a Jew, a Phyſitian by Profeſſion, ſlighting that which the Magiſtrates had deſigned for her. That Action much amaz'd both the Senate, whoſe Honourable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception and Entertainment ſhe refus'd; and the Prieſts of the Town, who enflam'd with the Zeal of God's Houſe, could not forbear to ſpeak in Publick againſt her, for her Ridiculous and Scandalous Choice of the Houſe of a man, who is by Profeſſion, <hi>a ſworn Enemy of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Yet this Meting, for all that, appeared to be ſomwhat too hard; and the wiſer ſort thought, That ſomthing ſhould have been allowed to the condition of a Queen, and that Excuſes ſhould be made for her. But ſhe replied for her ſelf, That Jeſus Chriſt had all his life-time converſed with the Jews; That himſelf was come of their Seed; and that he had preferred their Company to the Company of all other Nations. Now judge ye your ſelves of this Anſwer. When ſhe went out of <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> it was at an unſeaſonable hour, to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113644:8"/>
wit, at 4 or 5 a Clock in the Morning, at the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going of a Feaſt, whereat the <hi>Land-grave of Heſſe</hi> had Royally entertain'd her, without taking her leave ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Senate, or of the Magiſtrates: whereat e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one was extremely ſurpriſed. In her Train ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fifth, or Sixth her ſelf, followed on her Voyage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the United Provinces, without being accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with any Woman, or Maid-ſervant: having left her two <hi>Hollands</hi>-Women (that had ſerved her a long enough time, and which ſhe had brought from <hi>Sweden</hi> with her) at <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> without giving them any Recompence, as ſhe had likewiſe done to her Foot-men and Coach-men: committing her ſelf wholly to the guidance of Seigneur <hi>Eſteenberg,</hi> of whom ſhe made choice above all in her Court, as of the moſt brutiſh and irrational man; and having given the Charge of the <hi>Maſter of her Houſhold,</hi> or Steward, to <hi>Silver-Crona,</hi> whoſe name full of Silver, ſmells rankly of her Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith.</p>
            <p>She continued her manner of acting in the <hi>Vnited Provinces,</hi> as ſhe had begun it in <hi>Denmark,</hi> and <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh.</hi> She entred theſe Countries alſo, without making her ſelf known, ſleighting the Preparations that the Lords the States-General of the <hi>Vnited Provinces,</hi> had made for an Honourable Reception of her: and in ſuch manner paſſed through their Towns, until ſhe came to give her ſelf up into the hands of the Spaniards.</p>
            <p>But her contentment here could not be full, ſince her good friend <hi>Pigmentelli</hi> is not here, who is the man, that hath taken the place of <hi>Bourdelot,</hi> and who did entirely poſſeſs her, all the time of his Negotiation in <hi>Sweden:</hi> for whom ſhe made Feaſts, Balles, Walks, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Rejoycings. And it is not without Reaſon, that many perſons ſuſpected, That it was this man, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113644:9"/>
made her aborſe that monſtrous Deſign, to quit the Crown; which ſhe ſayes ſhe had conceived a long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough time before, in her Letter that ſhe wrote to Monſieur <hi>Chanut,</hi> Ambaſſador for the King of <hi>France,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the States-General of the Low-Countries. It was he only, that did eat oft'neſt with her, that accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied her in all her Walks, that entertain'd her at night until 3 or 4 a Clock after mid-night; and laſtly, who was her <hi>Achates,</hi> or inſeparable Companion, and who did no leſs all her buſineſs, than his Predeceſſor <hi>Bourdelot.</hi> It is a great change, To come out of the hands of a <hi>Frenchman,</hi> to fall into the arms of a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> that hath had ſo great a power over her minde, as to obliege her, and make her ſay to the Ambaſſador of <hi>Portugal, That ſhe acknowledged not his Maſter, as King of that Country, but only as Duke of</hi> Bregance. Other Miniſters of State have been little better uſed of her. For there is none of them all, from one end to the other, that hath not been neglected: which alſo made them take that reſolution, to baniſh themſelves from the Court, whither they went no more, than their Maſter's Affairs call'd them to it. I muſt not forget that famous Ball, which the Queen made Dance for the farewel to her deereſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident; whereof ſhe would bear a part, and repreſent therein the perſon of the <hi>Woman-Fool,</hi> or <hi>Pratling-Houſwiſe.</hi> Whilſt ſhe was Apparelling her ſelf, ſhe took a fair Diamond from off her finger, and gave it to <hi>Pigmentelli</hi> to keep it for her: which, ſo ſoon as ſhe had on her Apparel, he offered to render her again. But ſhe replied, <hi>That ſhe had never uſed to take that again, which ſhe had once given.</hi> The Stone was eſteem'd at 30 or 40 thouſand Livers. But what ſhall we ſay of that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage Extraordinary, which ſhe ſent to his Catholick Majeſty, only to thank him, that he had ſent her ſo gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant a man, as <hi>Pigmentelli?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:113644:9"/>If theſe great Perſons, which ſhe hath called to her at divers times, had been ſomwhat others than they were, without doubt they had been both better received, and more honourably uſed. Monſieur <hi>Naudeus,</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able longer to ſuffer the Diſorders and Looſeneſs of that Court, wherein the Muſes were no more hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſaw himſelf conſtrained to baniſh himſelf from it, of his own accord; and did prefer a voluntary Exile, to an abode ſo little favourable to men of Learning, whom that Princeſs had loved for ſome time; but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that <hi>Bourdelot</hi> had put that high gallantry into her head, there was no more to do for them: And all the fair appearances, that ſhe had ſhewn them, were nothing but made countenances, or rather a remainder as it were of her firſt Opinions. I call them all to witneſs, if there be found any one of them, that hath been either fully, or reaſonably ſatisfied, except one, or two, who knew well how to take their time.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>Bouchard,</hi> whoſe Vertue and Knowledge render him worthy of eternal Memory, was uſed like a Pedant in that Court. The Queen often complained, That he had but very little gallantry in him: and when ſome repreſented to her, That gallantry agreed not well with the Profeſſion he made; ſhe anſwer'd, that ſhe made but very little eſteem of a man, that knew nothing but how to read on a Book; and that for being informed in ſome words of Arabick, her approbation was not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to be gained: As if Monſieur <hi>Bouchard</hi> had ever cared much for it. This he well witneſſed, When the Queen advertiſing him of the Deſign ſhe had to quit the Crown, and demiſe the Adminiſtration of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to retire her ſelf into a Solitude, in the company of ſome knowing men, of the Number of whom ſhe wiſhed, That he would be one: He did not ſo much as once to Anſwer her Letter. And his ſilence ought
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113644:10"/>
not to be reputed other than very reaſonable; ſince he did well in it; and the iſſue hath made it be ſeen, that ſhe was full of Hypocriſie, and that what the Queen was doing in the Buſineſs, was nothing but Deceit, for diſguiſing the Deſign ſhe had, of running a courſe of <hi>Light-houſwifery.</hi> But let us ſuppoſe that the thing was, as ſhe deſcribed it; yet Monſieur <hi>Bouchard</hi> had Reaſon to be ſilent, having been worſe uſed, than can be well imagined; in that they left him to a lodging for the ſpace of ſix weeks, before they made ſo much as a ſhew to viſit him: And that he was very ill rewarded, after the pains he had taken to come to <hi>Sweden,</hi> only to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Queens deſire.</p>
            <p>The good Counſels that this Princeſs gave, and the leſſon that ſhe taught to the deceaſed Monſieur <hi>de Saumaiſe</hi> his little Son, is a thing very pleaſant to hear. Moſt people know, That after the death of this great man, whoſe Memory the Queen honoured with a Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral-Oration, which ſhe made a Profeſſor of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſity of <hi>Vpſal</hi> make; ſhe wrote a fine Letter to the Lady, his Widow, wherein ſhe ſet forth her purpoſe of Educating her Son, that was the only Child, of all that Monſieur <hi>de Saumaiſe</hi> had, appointed to Studies. The Mother, to diſcharge her ſelf of this, as well as of her elder Sons, ſent him into <hi>Sweden:</hi> to whom this Princeſs, when he came to do his Reverence unto her, and to Kiſs her Hand, repreſented, that ſhe would not that he were only knowing, as was his Father; but that ſhe moreover deſired, that he were a very gallant ſpirit, and learned with much care the Faſhion, wherewith to govern himſelf at Court: that a Gentleman ought to make as much Profeſſion of Gallantry at the leaſt, as of Letters. This fine Leſſon read unto a yong Boy, ſubject as yet unto the Rod, and to Correction, made ſo great
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113644:10"/>
an impreſſion in his minde, that after that, he was heard to ſpeak of little elſe, but of going to viſit the Ladies of the Court, and of Vaulting and Dancing. This good Princeſs did take ſo great a care of him, that ſhe ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to ſtay all the time he was in <hi>Sweden,</hi> in a Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alling-houſe, ſo ill appointed, that he looked rather like a Beggar, than a Gentleman's Son of good Birth. And to aſcend back again from the Son to the Father, it is true, that this Perſonage ſeems to have been better uſed, than any other man of Letters: and yet for all that, he departed out of <hi>Sweden</hi> diſcontented enough; whereof I profeſs that I knew not the Reaſons. Yet I have ſeen of his Letters in <hi>Sweden,</hi> written to ſome of his Friends, which ſaid, That he repented him in ſome ſort, that he had deſerved the approbation of the Queen, ſeeing ſhe was ſo eaſie to give it to Perſons, that were altogether unworthy. But I know well, that ſo he hath been ſpoken of in that Court, for a Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> whoſe Wife wore the Breeches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Voſsius</hi> and <hi>Heinſius,</hi> if they will tell the truth, have no great cauſe, to be the beſt contented with her, of the world. <hi>Voſsius</hi> hath had all the pains, that can be imagined, to make himſelf to be paid off that which he had laid out for the Queen, in buying of divers Books, which he had done for her. And <hi>Heinſius</hi> is yet to ſue for what is due to him, for the like cauſe, and moreover for the Services that he did her Majeſty. Judge by this, if men of Learning be in any great real eſteem with her. Without doubt, had they been leſs knowing, and more gallant, that their buſineſs had been better carried through, according to the Example of <hi>Bourdelot,</hi> whom the Queen hath given her Paſs to, as the excellenteſt and firſt amongſt men in the world. And I can aſſure you thus much, that he could not ſpeak congruous Latin.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113644:11"/>
I have ſeen a <hi>Note</hi> written with his own hand, to a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop that had been chaſed out of his Country for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and that did implore her Majeſties aſſiſtance by his interceſſion: In which <hi>Note,</hi> within the compaſs of 4 or 5 lines, which it did contain, I found Three or Four Soloeciſms and Barbariſms: And the ſenſe of the whole ſo confuſed, that there was need to go to a Wizard, for to have it made plain. This <hi>Note</hi> is yet in the hands of a man unblamable, that is in <hi>Sweden;</hi> at leaſt, if he be not come out of it ſince my ſelf: the which without doubt he keeps, to put it in the <hi>Vatican,</hi> or in the Kings Library at <hi>Paris,</hi> for an Authentick Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the profound knowledge of <hi>Bourdelot,</hi> who to the Queen of <hi>Sweden</hi> vaunted, and chanted ſo much, becauſe he could make ſome ſorry ryming French verſes, though neither that, but imperfectly enough. If it be poſſible for me to get a Copy of this <hi>Note,</hi> I ſhall impart it to the Publick, with ſome other Memorials, that I expect from <hi>Sweden;</hi> whereby you ſhall know, whether <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delot</hi> be ſo great a man, as the Queen hath made him paſs for; and whether he had reaſon to cenſure all the great men that went to <hi>Sweden,</hi> and the Latine Poeſies of Monſieur <hi>Maurus</hi> (whoſe knowledge is known, chiefly in all the Countries of the Lords the Eſtates General of the United Provinces) wherein he found, that the word <hi>Poſteri,</hi> was not good Latine, but that he ſhould have ſaid, <hi>Poſteritas;</hi> whereunto the Queen applauded, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Bourdelot</hi> had ſaid it. It is ſurely a matter of Aſtoniſhment, why a Princeſs ſo well furniſhed with Light of Knowledge, ſuffered her ſelf ſo ſtrongly to be blinded by this infamous fellow: which even the meaneſt of the Commons in <hi>Sweden</hi> having obſerved, they perſwaded themſelves that he had a familiar Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and that he uſed Charms to bewitch her Minde:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113644:11"/>
I have heard it ſaid by many, whilſt I was in <hi>Sweden.</hi> And when I attempted to put this conceit out of their heads, as being a Flout, or as a Dull conceit; I found them ſo deeply perſwaded of it, that my attempt was without effect.</p>
            <p>But what ſhall we ſay of the horrible injuſtice that this Princeſs hath done to her Creditors? When I look upon it, I tremble; and think that thoſe, who have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken her demiſing the Crown as a famous playing the Bankrupt, had ſome reaſon for it. It is ſeen, (I am a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it) that there be ſome Merchants of Jewels, from whom ſhe had taken up Goods, from ſome for Ten, from others for Twenty, and from ſome for Thirty thouſand Livres, to whom ſhe hath delay'd payment to be made, for Six, for Ten, and for Fifteen months beyond the time, yea, two yeers, and in the end went her way, leaving Tickets, that will be paid <hi>ad Calendas Graecas,</hi> that is, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Is it not a matter of aſtoniſhment, and which cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for vengeance to God, that theſe poor people have been forced to leave off their lawful occaſions and buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to conſume their Livelihood, in attendance for their own in a ſtrange Country, where the expences are great; and, at laſt, to ſee themſelves left empty handed? But be not at all aſtoniſhed at this: <hi>Bourdelot</hi>'s Maxime, which the Queen hath exactly followed, was this: <hi>That Kings might diſpoſe of the goods of private men, as they pleaſed.</hi> But whence hath he drawn this falſe doctrine? With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, from the bottom of his black and baſe ſoul. I have ſeen ſome of theſe Merchants with all poſſible earneſtneſs deſire their Jewels back again, ſince they ſaw themſelves out of hope to be paid: but they were in the hands of a Princeſs, that had a heart rather to give them away to others, then ever to render them to their right owners. This was not for want of information of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113644:12"/>
wrong was done theſe men: for ſhe was ſufficiently ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſed thereof, by Petitions and Requeſts which they preſented to her; all which ſhe received from them, and read them upon her pierced Chair, and then wip'd her hinder parts with them.</p>
            <p>But what Juſtice can be expected from that perſon, that doth not right to her ſelf? Look a little on her car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage in the Oeconomy of her houſe. Her <hi>Intendant,</hi> to whom ſhe ſent all her Creditors, was a man that could neither reade, nor write, except onely his name, which he learn'd to ſcribble a little time ſince. He was a Taylor by trade, and was called <hi>Maſter Iohn;</hi> whoſe Needle &amp; Shears this Princeſs hath changed to a Sword, he being made a Noble-man; and hath given him the name of <hi>Lyon Crona:</hi> but truly he carries the likeneſs of a Monkey, rather then of a Lion. This illuſtrious Blade knew ſo well how to govern the Queens minde, that ſhe committed to him the <hi>Intendancie</hi> and <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of her whole houſe: who following his Miſtreſs's Genius, he ſtudied, in the midſt of his Ignorance, to deceive the world; and made himſelf ſo knowing in that Art, that there was none, but ſuch as had no buſineſs with him, that have eſcaped his Knaveries. He began to enrich himſelf, by the Voyage he made into <hi>France,</hi> for the proviſions of the Queens Coronation; from whence having brought an heap of the worſt Stuffs, he made Merchandiſe of them in <hi>Sweden</hi> after this manner: When the Queen gave commiſſion to her domeſticks, or others, to make them Cloaths, <hi>Mr. Iohn</hi> directed them to the Merchant with whom he had intruſted his Magazine; ſo a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by this means they were conſtrained at laſt to go to him, who gave them wares of the value of 50 Crowns, for 100; which they entered into Recognizance to pay him for: which change was not over diſadvantageous to him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:113644:12"/>To paſs from the <hi>Intendant,</hi> to the <hi>Vallets of; her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> who in in their own kinde governed alſo the Queen: they were perſonages worthy to be known. One of them was called <hi>du Piquet,</hi> a French-man by Nation, who was the moſt infamous Pimp in the world; and his wife had been kept in priſon at <hi>Bruxels</hi> or <hi>Antwerp,</hi> for her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous tricks. The other of them was call'd <hi>Alexander,</hi> an Italian born, who they ſay <hi>drew his illuſtrious extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from a very renowned Cobler.</hi> And both theſe were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The Queens Piggs;</hi> whom ſhe made Noble-men, though they had never been remarkable for any thing, but Infamy and Baſeneſs. If it was, becauſe they had ſerved her, there were an hundred others, who have had that honour, and who did it more honourably, and with more faithfulneſs, and more glory. See here how this Princeſs kept the laws of Juſtice in all her carriage.</p>
            <p>Ask, if you pleaſe, the <hi>Gentlemen of her Chamber,</hi> and her <hi>Maids of Honour;</hi> you ſhall finde, that in a moment ſhe quitted her ſelf of them all, and of her Pages alſo, without ſo much as paying them their allowances; to ſay nothing of Recompence, which is no more to be found neer her.</p>
            <p>Speak but a little to the <hi>Secretary of her Commands,</hi> who ſerved her eighteen months with an incredible diligence and fidelity, and who cauſed more to be writ in his time to the Queen, and to Kings, and to all the Princes of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> than all his predeceſſors had done: He will tell you, that ſhe was ingrate to him, in this, that ſhe left him not a <hi>ſous,</hi> although he made all the petty expences of the Cabinet, himſelf.</p>
            <p>It is not long time ſince ſhe had made a <hi>Neapolitan Gentleman</hi> come from <hi>Rome,</hi> and had written to Madam the <hi>Dutcheſs of Aiguillon,</hi> that he ſhould not repent for having come to her ſervice; becauſe <hi>ſhe knew not onely how
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113644:13"/>
to acknowledge the ſervices that any did her, but alſo to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe them, even to their good wills that they ſhould teſtifie to have for her.</hi> But all theſe fair words were without any real effect, and were but winde, that is diſſipated; or as ſmoak, that vaniſheth: and they left this poor Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (though he was of very good birth) amongſt the troop of thoſe that were miſerable.</p>
            <p>But what ridiculous entertainment did ſhe give that <hi>French Gentleman,</hi> that brought to her the <hi>little young Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de Saumaize,</hi> who for ſome reaſon, that I will not here mention, voluntarily baniſhed himſelf out of <hi>France,</hi> and from his own houſe; and who had undertaken that ſorry condition, either to acknowledge the obligations that he had to the deceaſed <hi>Monſieur de Saumaize,</hi> or that he was perſwaded, that this Princeſs, being a great Queen, he might hope to receive from her all manner of ſatisfaction, when ſhe ſhould be informed of his worth and valour? we ſaw him neglected in <hi>Sweden,</hi> as much, or more then any other; and ſhe ſuffered him to go his way, without giving him any thing at all, as an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the pains he had taken for her, and the care he had taken of that little childe. Is not here a brave way of knowing how to <hi>recompenſe ſo far, as to reach even the good will that any had towards her?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot omit the mentioning of the injuſtice that was done to a <hi>Valet of the Barderob,</hi> called by the name of <hi>du Pleſsis,</hi> a French-man by Nation; who for having made himſelf too watchful towards his Miſtreſſes ſervice (who thereby perhaps was hindered of her night-practices with <hi>Pigmentelli</hi>) cauſed him one evening to be beaten by her Foot-men, diſguiſed in gray cloaths: which he got of her, in recompenſe of all his ſervices done her, and his great diligence. A brave faſhion, ſurely, of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging her ſervants!</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:113644:13"/>I omit many others; as, the <hi>Governour of her Pages,</hi> called <hi>La Selle,</hi> who having a twofold charge in the Queens houſe, carryed himſelf therein with a behaviour ſo wiſe, and ſo diſcreet, that her ſelf confeſſed, that ſhe had nothing to ſay againſt him; whoſe merit therefore made him be choſen for his Highneſs the <hi>Prince Atolf,</hi> to accompany him in his travels: who yet was no better uſed by her, than others. He is come out of <hi>Sweden,</hi> full of Honours indeed, but very empty of money, at leaſt, for any that he had from the Queen. A great Princeſs indeed, and worthy that perſons of honour and quality ſhould ſerve her!</p>
            <p>But before we lay aſide the Pen, for a farewel, let us ſpeak a little to our <hi>French Muſicians.</hi> When the <hi>Count Magnus de la Garde</hi> was ſent Ambaſſadour to the moſt Chriſtian King of <hi>France,</hi> by her Majeſtie of <hi>Sweden;</hi> he gave commandment for the choice of a Company or Set of Violins or Muſicians; to whom, by contract ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his hand, he promiſed conditions very reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Theſe poor people engaged themſelves for their voyage into <hi>Sweden,</hi> where at the beginning they were uſed favourably enough; whether it was, that the Queen is much pleaſed with new things; or, that ſhe found the harmony of the French Violins was better and more charming than that of Viels, or Swediſh Timbrels: But that laſted no long time; and at this day they are in ſuch miſery, that there be ſome of them, who are indebted for all their expences ſince their wages dried up, ſo that it was not poſſible for them, by any ſollicitations or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits they made, to get any part of that which was ſo authentically promiſed them. The Queen danced in the Balls and Ballets, to the cadence of their Violins, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til ſhe withdrew behinde the Theatre; from whence none of them could ſee her return, to furniſh them with
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113644:14"/>
Strings; ſo that I think they may now hang up their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments on a hook. But why did not you, as thoſe gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Italians did, who deſired leave to be gone, as ſoon as they wanted money; and were ſtuffed up with Rheums and Flegms, when their purſes were empty? Your gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſs hath marred you; and you have ſeen, that for having too much ſlackned of that which was your due, your Inſtruments are unſet.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſs, thoſe that reade what I write, will hardly believe it. But let him believe it that will, I am fully aſſured, that ſuch as have ſeen the eſtate of the Court of <hi>Sweden,</hi> or have been truly informed thereof, will know I ſpeak leſs thereof than what may be ſaid: and I would bring nothing hither, <hi>I have not ſeen my ſelf.</hi> When I ſhall have received the Memorials that I am promiſed out of <hi>Sweden,</hi> I ſhall impart them to the Publike, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceive it in many things. I hope to receive them by ſome French-man, of whom that Country now disbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens her ſelf by little and little, and who were well ſhaken when I came away. You may have patience, if you pleaſe, till that time; when you may know ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more private and particular of Queen <hi>Chriſtina:</hi> or if not, take this further account at preſent. She go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards <hi>Bruxels,</hi> was met on her way four miles from that City, by the Archduke <hi>Leopoldus,</hi> and many Gallants of his Court; by whom ſhe was conducted to the ſaid Duke's Palace, where ſhe was entertained with Plays, Balls, Feaſts, and all Gallantry imaginable. She was Royally feaſted by the Earl of <hi>Fuenſaldagne,</hi> who (for that end) ſent Letters to ſeveral Cities and Towns in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> for Rarity and Variety: to the Citie of <hi>Gant,</hi> for Veal; to <hi>Bruges,</hi> for Capons; to <hi>Antwerp,</hi> for Fiſh; to <hi>Mons,</hi> for Mutton; to <hi>Ardine,</hi> for Veniſon; to <hi>Lille</hi> and <hi>Torney,</hi> for Poultry of all ſorts. Theſe preſented
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113644:14"/>
themſelves by troops, to welcom her to <hi>Bruxels.</hi> But no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be more pleaſing to her, then the ſweet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>Pigmentelli;</hi> who was complacent not only in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his perſon, but alſo in regard of the ſtately pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents ſent from his Maſter the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived no ſmall joy at the reception of that Royal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert into his Dominions. Thus ſhe deluded Time with variety of Delights, until the Duke's departure to the Army; whom ſhe preſented with a Gallant Horſe, ſumptuouſly accoutred with Gold and Diamonds to a very great value. In <hi>September</hi> ſhe departed thence, bending her courſe for <hi>Italy,</hi> with a very numerous Train; poſting it thorow the Country after her wonted man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; having alſo a long Tail of Jeſuites and Friers, which ſhe trailed after her to <hi>Inſpruck</hi> in <hi>Tirol,</hi> the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Grand Duke of that Country; where her entertainment was extraordinary, and where all the Nobility and Gentry in the Country were by the Duke ſummoned to appear, in all their Pomp, to attend the ſolemn and actual Apoſtatization of this wretched Queen; which was performed thus: She was led by the Archduke to the Franciſcan Church, (attended by a numerous company) where ſhe was ſeated under a Canopie on the left hand, before the high Altar: below her, toward the right hand, were the Archduke and his Lady: over againſt them, <hi>Pigmentelli</hi> the Spaniſh Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, in a Chair by himſelf. The Quire was hung with Crimſon-Velvet, and the ground covered with Red Serge. <hi>Holſteinus</hi> the Popes Nuntio ſtood on the right ſide of the Altar, and ſpake thus: <hi>That Pope</hi> Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander <hi>the Seventh having underſtood that</hi> Chriſtina <hi>Queen of Sweden had an intent to put her ſelf into the boſome of the Church, had ſent his Letters to teſtifie his approbation of her deſires, and his readineſs to receive her with his Apoſtolical
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113644:15"/>
benediction: therefore he was there to know whether it was true or no.</hi> To which ſhe anſwered in the Affirmative, Then <hi>Holſteinus</hi> deſired, <hi>That in teſtimony of the truth thereof, ſhe would make profeſsion of the Romane Faith, and ſwear to keep it, on the holy Evangeliſts:</hi> which ſhe did, and kiſs'd the Book. Immediately on this, a Chair was ſet for <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteinus</hi> to ſit in, and a Cuſhion laid at his feet, on which the Queen kneeled: and then he making the ſigne of the Croſs over her head, and embracing her ſhoulders, gave her Abſolution from all the ſins ſhe had committed. Then were certain ſhort Prayers ſaid (or rather ſung) in Latine, for her: after which, high Maſs was ſung; and then a Prieſt made a Sermon in Dutch, wherein he exhorted her to forget her People, Country, and Fathers houſe, and to ſtick cloſe to that profeſſion ſhe had taken up. Afterwards, <hi>Te Deum</hi> was ſung with excellent Voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Inſtruments of all ſorts, and Drums, (which I never ſaw before in a Church.) All was concluded with the diſcharge of Ordnance, and other demonſtrations of great joy. At night, the Archduke entertained her with a Mask, and Dancing. Here ſhe tarried not long, but departed towards <hi>Italy.</hi> In her way ſhe took <hi>Bologne,</hi> where ſhe was met by the Popes Legat, who was ſent to congratulate her arrival. From thence ſhe went to <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retto,</hi> where ſhe offered up a Crown and Scepter to the Idol of the place. Here ſhe ſhewed great external de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, which ſhe performed with many Ceremonies. Nothing remained now, but that ſhe caſt her ſelf into the Arms of the Pope; to which purpoſe, ſhe addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her ſelf towards <hi>Rome,</hi> where great preparation was made for her reception: but ſhe, to ſhew her great hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, ſent a Letter beforehand to that holy Father, praying that all ſuch Preparations might be moderated. At her arrival, ſhe was admitted on her knees to kiſs the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113644:15"/>
hands and feet of the Pope. Having now lodg'd her at <hi>Rome,</hi> I leave her there; wiſhing ſhe would ſeriouſly ruminate on thoſe words of our Saviour, <hi>He</hi> (or ſhe) <hi>that denies me before men, him</hi> (or her) <hi>will I deny before my Father which is in heaven;</hi> whereby ſhe might become ſenſible of her follies, and finde favour at laſt with that God, whom ſhe hath greatly offended by this her abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Apoſtacie and Backſliding.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>The GENIUS of <hi>CHRISTINA</hi> Queen of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ARS,</hi> whom the common opinion makes the Crafts-maſter of Gallant Spirits, and whom Aſtrologians openly proclaim to preſide at the births of great men, having adopted for his ſon the Illuſtrious <hi>Guſtavus of Sweden;</hi> in conſideration of his extraordinary gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity of minde, Reſolved that the adoption he had made of this great King, ſhould be ratified in the Common-Councel of the gods, that it might be the more authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113644:16"/>
and at the ſame time obtained of that Supreme Senate, that deliberation might be had about a Succeſſor to him, that might not degenerate from him in any of his high qualities. The terms made uſe of by <hi>Mars,</hi> to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige the firſt of all the gods to convocate this Aſſembly of deities, were uttered thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Greatest of the gods, you that are the diſpenſer of happineſs and of misfortune in humane affairs; you, that eſtabliſh Thrones, and overturn them when you pleaſe; Vouchſafe to cast your eyes upon the happineſs of</hi> Sweden, <hi>unto which I have given one of the greatest Monarchs that this day reigns over men, and whoſe Generoſity conſtrains me to avouch him for my Son: Do me the favour, that the choice I have made of ſo great a King, may be accepted of by the whole Court of heaven. The gods are too juſt, not to ſecond ſo equitable a purpoſe. It will be enough, that you, from your Soveraign Authority, call together the Aſſembly; in which I would wiſh, that moreover delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be had for a Succeſſor to Grand</hi> Guſtavus, <hi>that may be a perfect imitator of his rare Vertues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iupiter</hi> having approved of the two Heads of <hi>Mars</hi> his requeſt, diſpatched <hi>Mercury</hi> preſently, to call toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Aſſembly of all the principal gods; to every one of whom he went, in their ſeveral quarters, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated to them the Orders of <hi>Iupiter;</hi> which imported, <hi>That every one of them ſhould be preſent in the place of their extraordinary Aſſemblies, within eight days; there to delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate of a buſineſs of great importance, that concerned the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of one of the greateſt Kingdoms in Europe.</hi> The time that <hi>Iupiter</hi> gave for the aſſembling of the gods, ſerved <hi>Mars</hi> to aſſure himſelf of ſome of the moſt powerful of them, whom he ſollicited with ſo much favour, that, in the end, he brought to his devotion all whom he believed could be moſt uſeful to him in this buſineſs. The time being expired, ſuch gods as had no lawful impediment,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113644:16"/>
obeyed the Orders without failing, that <hi>Mercury</hi> had imparted unto them from <hi>Iupiter:</hi> and the Aſſembly was found to conſiſt of <hi>Saturn, Minerva, Venus, Mercury,</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> himſelf, who was the preſident thereof. He ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving declared the reaſons of this their extraordinary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocating, ordered <hi>Mars</hi> to utter what he had to ſay: who ſpake after this manner:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ye just gods, that watch inceſſantly over the government of mortal men; you, who are always equally ready to recompenſe vertue, and to puniſh vice: Give, of your good favour, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to one of the juſtest requests that can ever be preſented to you.</hi> Sweden <hi>(which at this day contains three of the most ancient Kingdoms of Europe) is in poſſeſsion of one of the greatest Princes of the world: His high vertues, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, cast more luſtre abroad, than the flowers of his Crown: His courage equals that of</hi> Caeſar, <hi>and of</hi> Alexander: <hi>His deſignes are full of Generoſity, that make him to be admired of all Europe, and render him formidable to all the Nations that it contains; and are irreproveable witneſſes, that he is the braveſt Spirit that can be found. Since therefore, by the irrevocable diſpoſal of the Destinies, I exerciſe the dominion over all great Courages; and that never any hath been ſeen, that ſurpaſſed this of</hi> Guſtavus the Great; <hi>I make authentick declaration, in preſence of all your Deities, that I have adopted him for my ſon; deſiring further from your juſtice, that ye will be pleaſed to confirm the election that I have made. And becauſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of mortal men permits them not alway to live upon earth, I ſupplicate this auguſt Aſſembly, that here it may be delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, how to give him ſuch a Succeſſor, as may make him live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain amongſt men, (when himſelf ſhall be placed amongſt the gods) by an expreſs imitation of all his rare perfections, which render him the object of admiration to all the world. All heads fit to bear Crowns, are in truth productions that come immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from heaven: they bear on their brow the character of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113644:17"/>
Divinity; they are our Images upon earth, and our Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, by whom we reign viſibly over men. But great Kings, ſuch as</hi> Guſtavus, <hi>are Demi-gods amongſt men, who want no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Immortality, to be perfect Deities. And our glory is intereſted to perpetuate the ſeed of theſe great Heroes on the earth, that men may adore our power in him, that we give to them; that they may be conſtrained to confeſs, that the gods are juſt and bountiful, to ſet over them ſuch powers, as are ſo accompliſhed; and that they may be in a continual poſture of ſending up the veneration that they have to their Maſters, ſo as it redound to the adoration they owe unto the gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The whole Aſſembly touched with the diſcourſe that <hi>Mars</hi> made thereto, and chiefly with the favourable Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morials that he gave them of the illuſtrious qualities of the Great <hi>Guſtavus;</hi> all the gods intereſſed themſelves with ſome heat, in a buſineſs that they judged very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant, and whereof everyone by himſelf alone de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to carry away the honour. There was not one, that approved not of the election which he had made, and did not ſubſcribe it with joy: which having taken back again from the hands of the gods, he put it in his pocket. <hi>Iupiter</hi> thanked him for the care he had taken to cultivate great perſonages; and exhorted him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the ſame, that ſo the authority of the gods might always flouriſh upon earth: and laſtly, he prayed the Aſſembly, that they would deliberate upon the ſecond point declared in the requeſt of <hi>Mars.</hi> Here <hi>Saturn,</hi> with his wrinkled brow, and gravity that looked towards the grave, in quality of the ancienteſt of the company, took upon him to ſpeak, and repreſented to the Aſſembly, That it was he that had the dominion over all cold Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates; and that Reaſon required, that he alone, with <hi>Mars,</hi> ſhould take the care to give <hi>Sweden</hi> a Succeſſor af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Guſtavus,</hi> which was one of the principal Countries
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113644:17"/>
upon which he had influence. But this Propoſal was found ſo ridiculous, that all the Aſſembly oppoſed it openly: and <hi>Minerva</hi> not being able longer to keep ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, ſpake after this manner:</p>
            <p>
               <q>It is not poſſible that the heaven ſhould form a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction reſembling the Great <hi>Guſtavus,</hi> if but onely one deity ſhould be employed in the bringing forth thereof. <hi>Saturn,</hi> that would have the glory of it to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alone, hath not activity enough to do it. And no one of us, that have our different and diſtinct perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, can collect all thoſe excellent qualities that are requiſite to one that ſhould ſucceed <hi>Guſtavus.</hi> Therefore I think it very equitable, that ſome number of this Aſſembly, and no one alone, be deputed to take pains in this buſineſs. And to prevent all conteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that may enſue upon this Deputation, it were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that the Lot ſhould decide it; or elſe, that each of us ſubmit himſelf to the determination of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> herein.</q> But <hi>Iupiter</hi> excuſed himſelf very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly, fearing that he might procure the indignation of ſome of the gods againſt himſelf, ſhould he prefer either of them before others: ſo that the Aſſembly reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with one accord to uſe the firſt Expedient. So the Lot being caſt, it fell upon <hi>Minerva, Venus, Mars,</hi> and <hi>Mercury:</hi> of whom <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Saturn</hi> having taken their leave, they withdrew themſelves to their own places, to give way to the other to uſe their endeavours peaceably in an affair of ſo great importance.</p>
            <p>The firſt point that was agitated amongſt them, was, to determine of what ſex the Succeſſor of <hi>Guſtavus</hi> ſhould be, ſeeing the number of gods and goddeſſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the work, was equal. After ſome diſpute on both ſides, <hi>Minerva</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> carried it, rather by a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevolent conceſſion of the two gods, than by ſtrength of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113644:18"/>
reaſon; becauſe <hi>Minerva</hi> had done <hi>Mercury</hi> ſome plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure but few days before; and <hi>Venus</hi> alſo had done <hi>Mars</hi> a ſecret favour, during the eight days of reſpite before the coming together of the Aſſembly. This being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, it was readily agreed further, That <hi>Venus</hi> ſhould faſhion her body at her diſcretion; <hi>Minerva</hi> ſhould give her an inclination to the Sciences; <hi>Mars,</hi> an humour Generous and Martial; and <hi>Mercury</hi> ſhould indue her with his lightneſs and inconſtancie of nature. And of the mixture of the influences of theſe four deities, as of the concourſe of the four Elements, it was, that <hi>Chriſtina the Great,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Guſtavus the Great,</hi> was made up.</p>
            <p>And in truth, he that will reflect upon the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable paſſages of her life, ſhall ſee in her a marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſpoſition to the knowledge of all things worthy; much of Generoſity, and a Lightneſs incredible. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerva</hi> had the firſt years of her life; <hi>Venus</hi> drew her off at laſt from her profound meditations and ſtudies, and ſet her on a height of Gallantry: <hi>Mercury</hi> taking his turn, to ſhew his power, made her caſt her ſelf down from a Throne, to take her walks about the world. But <hi>Mars</hi> hath always had the Aſcendent during the whole courſe of her life, to this preſent: for it muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that whether ſhe gave her ſelf to ſtudie, or to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſements, or to Walks, that in all things ſhe ſhewed her ſelf a very generous Queen. During her under-age, ſhe was obſerved to take pleaſure in all the Exerciſes that might beſeem the perfection of a Princeſs: and that with ſuch towardlineſs, that thereby ſhe gave ground of very great and extraordinary hopes concerning her. So ſoon as her Wit was ſomewhat ripened, that ſhe ſaw her ſelf capable of the knowledge of gallant things, ſhe ceaſed not to take pains for the acquiring a perfect
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113644:18"/>
knowledge therein. She ſought out for the greateſt men in <hi>Europe,</hi> to ſatisfie this her natural greedineſs that ſhe had after all kinde of Knowledge. This Princeſs hath been ſeen, in the coldeſt days of Winter, in that cold Country, to riſe by four of the clock in the morning, to have communion with the Muſes in her Cabinet; where ſhe ſtayed commonly until nine, when ſhe was to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for her appearing in publike, and to the Council of her Kingdom, where ſhe ſhewed an admirable depth of wit, by the ready and ſubtil reſolutions that ſhe gave upon all ſorts of affairs that were there propoſed. The Divertiſements that ſhe loved beſt, were, to be conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant with knowing perſonages, and with them to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune about ſome point of learning. Her ordinary En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments were very different from ſuch as for the moſt part are uſed in Courts, eſpecially in any Court whereof a woman is the head. Her pooreſt entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was as good, as the profoundeſt ſtudies of the greateſt Doctor of the <hi>Sorbonne</hi> could have given: and one would eaſily have believed, to hear this Princeſs ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo many excellent things, that ſhe had had ſecret communication with ſome Goddeſs, that inſpired her with ſuch high knowledge: yea, I perſwade my ſelf, that ſhe might eaſily have gain'd the ſame opinion of her ſelf, amongſt that groſs-witted people of <hi>Sweden,</hi> as the Ceremonious <hi>Pompilius</hi> had amongſt the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> before they were poliſhed, &amp; whilſt they yet ſlept in the rudeneſs of ſuch perſons as inhabit Foreſts and Mountains. The extraordinary aſſiduity, wherewith ſhe gave her ſelf to the reading of all books of greateſt worth, ſo repleniſhed her minde with ſparkling light, that in one hour ſhe uttered more choice &amp; rare ſayings, then is ordinarily done in a whole year, in the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Univerſity of <hi>Europe;</hi> and one moment of her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113644:19"/>
gave more inſtruction, than an hundred leſſons taken from the greateſt Doctor of <hi>Salamanca.</hi> Hath any ever ſeen a Princeſs poſſeſs the knowledge of nine or ten Tongues, as ſhe doth? If Hiſtory vaunteth of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſo much, that ſhe could hold diſcourſe in good French with the French Ambaſſadour, in perfect Caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian with the Ambaſſadour of <hi>Spain,</hi> and in very refined Tuſcan with the Princes of <hi>Italy:</hi> what praiſes ſhall be recorded in favour of the <hi>Great Chriſtina,</hi> who can hold diſcourſe almoſt with all the Nations in <hi>Europe,</hi> in their own Languages? Hiſtory can never ſpeak ſo well of this Princeſs, as ſhe ſpeaks of it; whereof ſhe hath an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable knowledge. She hath learned all the Sciences that are called Humane, with ſo much perfection, that there is no Author, Greek or Latine, yea even the moſt difficult Poets, which ſhe doth not expound with a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous facility. The Mathematicks, Philoſophy Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Moral, have not eſcap'd her knowledge; which ſhe hath carryed along even unto Theologie, whereof I have heard her diſcourſe with an incredible ſubtilty. Behold, what the Genius of the Great <hi>Chriſtina</hi> hath been, under the Empire of <hi>Minerva!</hi> to whom <hi>Venus</hi> ſucceeded.</p>
            <p>This gentle Goddeſs, that had but ſorrily acted her part in the formation of the body of this Princeſs, ſhe being but poorly furniſhed with thoſe accommodations requiſite to the beauty of a woman, (for ſhe is little, and crooked, having a hollow bending on one ſide, that ſpoils the grace of her walking) would yet have it to be ſeen, that this body, ſo poorly faſhioned, was ſufficiently ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the higheſt ſort of Gallantries: and after <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina</hi> had abandoned the Muſes, ſhe was obſerved to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light her ſelf in Dancing and Balls, wherein ſhe had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the better. Such diſcourſes as were moſt diſſolute,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113644:19"/>
pleaſed her beſt; and wanton poſtures liked her better by far, than a modeſt behaviour. Great men for Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as <hi>Bouchard</hi> and <hi>Naudaeus</hi>) were in no more eſteem with her, becauſe they were not more gallant than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came them; and their demeanour was accounted by her ridiculous, becauſe they were too ſerious, and too mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt. I have heard her tell ſuch tales, as modeſty will not permit me to commit to writing: and I know an Eccleſiaſtical perſon of high degree, with whom I had contracted a very ſtrict amity in <hi>Sweden,</hi> that hath recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated her an hundred times, by telling her ſuch ſtories as the moſt diſſolute woman would hardly have born. Out of this high ſtrain of Gallantry, or rather Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luteneſs, whereof ſhe made a publike profeſſion, ſhe ſtep'd into impietie; and thoſe fair lights that ſhe had acquired by ſtudie, and which before had ſerved to regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late her manners, furniſhed her now with reaſons and arguments to fight againſt the ſacred Myſteries of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion. She hath not onely been ſeen to doubt of that ſacred Myſtery of the Incarnation, but even alſo to mock at it; and to ſay, in imitation of <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth of the Houſe of <hi>Medici, That Fable of Chriſt is very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for the Romane Kitchin.</hi> She ſpake not of <hi>Divine Providence,</hi> but under the term of <hi>Deſtiny,</hi> after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Profane Authors.</p>
            <p>Her chief Maximes were,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That we ought to love God, as the fountain of all good; but that we ſhould not fear him at all: becauſe it were a ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous thing, to fear a Being that is eſſentially good, and is inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of evil. But that we ought to fear evil men, that can hurt us a thouſand ways, and which are the onely devils, whereof the common people have ſo ſtrong a belief.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That a right-ſet minde ſhould never either repent, or pardon; becauſe repentance and pardon are always accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113644:20"/>
with unmanlineſs, or baſe-mindedneſs. That indeed a perſon ought always to conſult upon that which he takes in hand; but that he ſhould take an irrevocable reſolution to follow it, and never change.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>That the moſt particular and ſelf-ended opinions, are the beſt, and ſoundeſt; and that that which men at this day call Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, is nothing but a poor illuſion of men, wherewith the moſt part are pleaſed to deceive themſelves. For what likelihood is there, that a Belief that blindeth a man, and forbids all reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt it, ſhould be true? What reaſon is there to believe that, which one cannot comprehend; yea, and to impoſe an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation on us to believe it? This is all one, as to deſire a man to put out his eyes, that he may ſee the better; and to put him in ſuch a condition, as that thereby ye may be able to perſwade him to the greateſt abſurdities in the world. And that from hence, the many Sects are found ſcattered over the earth, are but ſo many pure dotages, and fond imaginations of ſome men, who have been deſirous to make themſelves famous, in declaring themſelves the heads of ſome parties: whereat ſhe wondered no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, becauſe there is no conceit or opinion ſo ridiculous, that hath not its followers.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>That the Doctrine of</hi> Plato <hi>of the univerſal ſoul of the world, could not be confuted, but with falſe Reaſons: and that ſhe could not perſwade her ſelf of the immortality of the ſoul, but by making it go and return into its own principle again; which is this univerſal ſoul, whereof our ſoul makes a part.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>That</hi> Moſes <hi>hath been as great an Impoſtor, as he was a good Wit. For ſhe could convince of falſhood the pretended Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous paſſage of the Iſraelites thorow the Red-ſea: foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as</hi> Numenius, <hi>Praefect of</hi> Antiochus, <hi>making War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Perſians, had got a famous Victory over thoſe Perſians in the ſame place, at ſuch a time, and in the ſame manner as</hi> Moſes <hi>did over</hi> Pharaoh; <hi>to wit, by obſervation of the flux and reflux of the Arabian Gulf.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:113644:20"/>I could ſay more, if her ſelf did not publiſh it by all her thoughts, which are now known to the greater part of <hi>Europe;</hi> and if I had not ſome horrour to ſet them down in writing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mercury</hi> ſeeing that this libertine humour, and with ſuch a bent carryed to all Gallantry, was too deeply rooted in her heart, and that ſhe as eaſily followed it to Recreations, as ſhe had done before to Studies; thought it to his purpoſe, to aſſociate himſelf with <hi>Venus;</hi> who was very well pleaſed with his company. So they ſtrove each with other, which of them ſhould make her the moſt <hi>Pratling Light-houſwife,</hi> or moſt inconſtant. But notwithſtanding this, Queen <hi>Chriſtina</hi> hath been noted for a long time, even from her Cradle, to be naturally of a very wavering minde; and that <hi>Mercury</hi> alſo had the dominion over her humour from her very infancie: But onely I begin to ſhew his Kingdom (to keep my order in what I write) ſince that change (almoſt unheard-of) that hath been made in the perſon of <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> when of a Soveraign ſhe made her ſelf a Subject; and preferred a vagabond and wandering life, to the glory and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence of a Throne. To ſay the truth, this thought had poſſeſſed her minde more than four or five years, before ſhe put it in execution; and it had been blamed by ſome great men, that had uſed their endeavour to diſſwade her from it. Monſieur <hi>Chanut</hi> Ambaſſadour of <hi>France,</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Saumaize,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>Spanheim,</hi> did their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to divert her from this purpoſe, which they judged would turn to her diſadvantage. But it was in vain. For the deſire ſhe had to ſee forraign Countries, and the new world, carryed her away from the wiſe counſels of thoſe perſons of quality. And ſo much power had Novelty and Change over her ſpirits, that ſhe turned her ſelf to all ſorts of objects, juſt as a Weather-cock is turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113644:21"/>
at the pleaſure of every winde. The laſt that came to her Court, were always moſt welcome, and moſt made of for a time, and received all imaginable te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of Amity; but yet without any effect, for the moſt part. For this lightneſs of minde in her, cauſed her to follow a kinde of Deceitfulneſs, of ſo fine a thred, that one could hardly take it up, or perceive it, but in a long proceſs of time, and after one had taken a great deal of pains in her ſervice, and expended much money, and then found himſelf far from being recompenſed for his ſervice, or ſatisfied for his disburſements. The needineſs of a thouſand perſons, that ſhe hath employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to ſatisfie her fantaſtical humours, cries with a loud voice for vengeance in the preſence of God, who, one may judge, according to appearance, hath left this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to a Reprobate-ſenſe; and given her goodly lights, that ſhe ſhould not ſee at all; and expoſed her to the laughter of all <hi>Europe,</hi> to ſatisfie, in part, his own juſtice. Since her fall, from which it is too probable ſhe will never riſe again, ſhe hath committed ſo many kindes of Extravagancies, that ſhe hath made her ſelf the Fable of all the world. A little written Piece, which one of my friends communicated to me, and which I believe to be common, deſcribes them well enough; which may ſuffice to give any one an account of them, that deſire to be informed concerning them. It is ſaid, that even at this day, amidſt the Spaniſh Gravity, ſhe ſhews ſo much levity, that the <hi>Venerable Fathers</hi> of the <hi>Society of Ieſus,</hi> have much ado, with all their wit, to know the temper of ſo Motley a <hi>Genius,</hi> that aſſumes more ſhapes and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, than ever <hi>Proteus</hi> himſelf did: They have ſo much ado, to know of what Religion ſhe is, that they that make it their only buſineſs to decide the points of Faith, cannot tell what to make of hers: They are in doubt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113644:21"/>
what to think of her Sex, becauſe ſometimes they ſee her in mens apparel, and ſometimes in womens; and for the moſt part, they ſee her in ſuch a faſhion as par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes of both, as if ſhe were an Hermaphrodite. Theſe great men (the Jeſuites) that at this day have the aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent over the mindes of ſo many Princes, have not been able as yet to diſcover, with what Byas this Princeſs muſt be handled. They finde her diſcourſe admirable; and ſo it is indeed; and beyond whatſoever one can imagine. Her cogitations are exceedingly raiſed above what is common; ſhe hath a fountain of Wit inexhauſtible; a ſtrong Reaſon, a charming Diſcourſe; a deportment as familiar as ſweet: but with all this, they are conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to confeſs, that they do not yet know <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> that changes her Affections as often as ſhe changes her Smock, and that loves and hates almoſt both at one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. When I look upon the diſgrace ſuſtained by Count <hi>Magnus de la Garde,</hi> wherein he fell with her, at that time when one would have thought that all ſhould have ſmiled upon him, and when there was neither ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, nor reaſon, that he ſhould have been removed from the Court, I flatter my ſelf, that I know the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> of the Queen ſomewhat neer, after a particular ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of her, and the moſt ſerious reflexions that I made upon ſo many ſeveral matters that came to paſs during the time of my ſojourning at <hi>Vpſal.</hi> And this hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged me to ſet down my thoughts, concerning which, I can anſwer any with truth, that they are free from paſſion, however they may ſeem not to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry favourable to this Princeſs: But yet they are more favourable than they may ſeem to be: for I proclaim with a loud voice, that I hold <hi>Chriſtina</hi> for the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary perſon of the world; for the cleareſt-ſight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113644:22"/>
and moſt knowing Queen, that hath ever appeared upon the earth: That her Diſcourſe is adorable, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to her Wit; That ſhe underſtands her ſelf well enough, to take up and know great ſpirits, and great men; and laſt, That ſhe is capable of the faireſt and moſt extraordinary atchievements, that ever have been done by any Heroical ſpirits in Antiquity. But if I ſay, that ſhe makes but little account of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; that ſhe hath a Faith very particular to her ſelf; that ſhe is a Deceiver, and inconſtant: there's none of thoſe, that ever had the honour to have frequented her Court, that doth not fully accord with me, and is not conſtrained to confeſs, that my conceptions of her do her no wrong. But if any accuſe me of too little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to a head that wore a Crown, to ſpeak thereof with ſuch liberty; I anſwer, that I owe her no ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect; but, to follow her own Maximes, I owe her ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the contrary, (although in truth I dare ſay, that I bear her no hatred) than any ſuch reſpect: I was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther born her Subject, nor her Slave; ſhe never did me any good, although ſhe was bound to have done it: And all the obligation that ever I had to her, that I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, was, that ſhe received me favourably, when I had firſt the honour to kiſs her hand; and that I deſerved to obtain her approbation, if I may believe the report that one made to me thereof, that had ordinary commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication with her. But I have learned, long ſince, to ſlight the approbation of four ſorts of perſons: that is to ſay, Of an Ignorant, becauſe he is uncapable of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the value of a thing; Of a Flatterer, becauſe he applaudeth for his own ends; Of a Deceiver, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ordinarily his thoughts are diſguiſed; and, Of a light and unconſtant perſon, becauſe the eſteem that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113644:22"/>
ſuch a one makes of any thing, is bred rather by Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and Humour, than from Reaſon.</p>
            <p>To ſay that <hi>Chriſtina</hi> is either ignorant, or a Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer, it cannot perhaps be affirmed with truth: but to believe that ſhe is a Deceiver, and Inconſtant, one will thereby do her no wrong. It muſt be confeſſed, for all this, that this Princeſs, amidſt all her capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and fantaſtical humours, and amidſt her Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantries, when ſhe gave greateſt attendance on her books, hath been carryed all along with an humour extraordinarily <hi>Martial,</hi> and full of Bravery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Minerva</hi> had ſometime the command of her mind: <hi>Venus</hi> poſſeſs'd it afterwards; and ſome do affirm, that ſhe poſſeſſes it as yet. <hi>Mercury,</hi> that had poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf of her from her Cradle, yet made no ſuch great ſhew of his power, as ſince he made her throw her ſelf down from a Throne. But <hi>Mars</hi> hath at all times governed the humour of <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> which hath not failed to drain all <hi>Sweden,</hi> to furniſh the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred greedineſs that ſhe hath, to give to others.</p>
            <p>Indeed, under the Reign of <hi>Minerva,</hi> ſhe hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd ſuch Liberalities, as were worthy of a Queen; and that to all great Perſonages that were ſent for by her, or that came to <hi>Sweden</hi> otherwiſe, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on particular occaſions of their own. Monſieur <hi>de la Tuillerie, Chanut,</hi> and <hi>Saumaize,</hi> may inform you of this.</p>
            <p>Under the Reign of <hi>Venus,</hi> he Largeſſes were not leſſened; whereof <hi>Bourdelot</hi> and <hi>Pigmentelli</hi> can tell you.</p>
            <p>And under <hi>Mercury,</hi> ſhe gave the rareſt Preſent that can be given from one to another. Speak but to the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> that reigns at this day, and he
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113644:23"/>
will confeſs, that it is by <hi>the Grace of God,</hi> and the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality of Chriſtina,</hi> that he ſits upon the Throne. The Medals coyn'd at the time of his Coronation, ſpeak it publikely: on the one ſide whereof, there is an arm holding a Crown, with this Inſcription under it; <hi>[FROM GOD, AND FROM CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STINA.]</hi> And even yet, now ſhe hath deveſted her ſelf of her Kingdom, ſhe uſeth ſuch profuſeneſs, as cannot but be the effects of a generous minde.</p>
            <p>Such perſons as have had experience of her all her life-time, report that ſhe ſhewed this liberal nature in a remarkable manner, even from her Cradle: and I believe with ſome reaſon, that it will continue with her to her Tomb.</p>
            <p>The Badge and Motto of that Order of Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood that ſhe inſtituted, ſets forth unto us a great bravery of her Spirit, which makes her even pretend to qualities that ſhe poſſeſſes not at all. She gave it the name of the Order of the <hi>Amaranth,</hi> or <hi>Flower-Gentle,</hi> with this Device or Motto, <hi>[Semper idem.]</hi> All men know, that this Flower fades not at all; and accordingly the Device above-ſaid doth perfectly well expreſs its immortal nature: and this is the Badge of her Order of Knighthood. But all men know as well, that know her, that there is nothing ſo changeable as <hi>Chriſtina;</hi> and that this invention doth very little reſemble her humour; the which notwithſtanding ſhe would thereby have had to paſs currant, for the moſt equitable and conſtant that ever was ſeen. She borrowed this Device from the now-deceaſed Cardinal <hi>Richlieu,</hi> in whom every thing was ſplendid and illuſtrious: but the application that ſhe made of it, was her own invention: not intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:113644:23"/>
thereby to blaze abroad the vertues of the <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranth,</hi> but the conſtancie of her own ſpirit, which ſhe would have had to be believed thereby, more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable then a Rock: but it was far otherwiſe, as hath been ſaid.</p>
            <p>Mans apparel that ſhe now wears, and which ſhe had before uſed ſometime in <hi>Sweden,</hi> where ſhe went cloathed almoſt like a Cavalier, are the tokens of an inclination that ſhe hath, to change her ſex into a more perfect: and although ſhe be in truth a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and ſo known to the world; yet ſhe uſeth the poſtures and faſhions of men, and will be fingering her Muſtaches, as though ſhe had ſome, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſhe hath none: thus deſiring to expreſs her ſtrong ambition to be what ſhe is not, and to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to be indeed ſo.</p>
            <p>And though all theſe conceits be but ridiculous, yet they repreſent to us ſome traces of a gallant ſoul, and a brave ſpirit, that would rather have been the inhabitant of a mans body, than of a womans, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that ſex is much raiſed above the other, and more proper for brave undertakings: that other ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been, as it ſeems, deſign'd by Nature to more lowe employments, and ſuch as are meaneſt in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſociety. But Great <hi>Chriſtina</hi> raiſing her ſelf above her female condition, puts her ſelf into ſuch poſtures and garbs, as may imitate and reſemble ſuch actions as are proper to men.</p>
            <p>She can ride admirably, and ſpur an horſe with ſuch dexterity, as if ſhe had been therein exerciſed ſome whole years in an Academy. She travels with a mans Periwig; her Hat garniſhed with a great Plume of Feathers, a Red Scarf, after the <hi>Spaniſh
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113644:24"/>
Faſhion;</hi> and they write from <hi>Bruxels,</hi> that ſhe hath ordered Arms to be made her, wherewith ſhe will head the <hi>Catholike Army,</hi> and go and confront the <hi>Mareſchal de Turenne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Muſt we not confeſs, that amidſt all theſe Follies, there is a great deal of Bravery? Since this <hi>Genius</hi> of hers, ceaſes not in them all, to form deſignes to it ſelf, that are above and beyond it.</p>
            <p>If this Pourtraict that I have made, ſeems to any to be too ſevere, let them pardon my diſpoſition, which is always to ſpeak the truth, where I think it is to the purpoſe. But to prevent all cenſures that more quick-ſighted perſons than my ſelf may give upon this Piece, I here ſubmit to them with all my heart: and when they ſhall give reaſons ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to inſpire me with other thoughts than thoſe which I have concerning the Genius of <hi>Chriſtina;</hi> I ſhall embrace them very willingly. It is not (as I have already confeſſed) that I have not a greater e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of her, than one can well imagine: but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as I have ſpoken both evil and good of her, I think I have ſpoken nothing but truth, thorowout: and the place wherein I write it, is ſuch, that it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits me to ſpeak the truth.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
